<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The confession and execution of Mr. Barney, who was hang'd at Norvvich; for the murder of Esq; Beddingfield which was commited on Sunday the 20th. of July 1684 With a true account of his behaviour during the time of his imprisonment, unto the day of his death, which was on the 8th. of Agust, 1684. As also a true account of the fire which happen'd in Goodmans Fields.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80315</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C5744B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R231316</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99897276</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99897276</idno>
            <idno type="VID">136980</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80315)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 136980)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2477:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The confession and execution of Mr. Barney, who was hang'd at Norvvich; for the murder of Esq; Beddingfield which was commited on Sunday the 20th. of July 1684 With a true account of his behaviour during the time of his imprisonment, unto the day of his death, which was on the 8th. of Agust, 1684. As also a true account of the fire which happen'd in Goodmans Fields.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet (2 p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by E.M. in Black-Horse Alley near Fleet-Bridge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Beddingfield, Thomas, d. 1684 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Barney, Thomas --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Last words --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Murder --  England --  Norwich --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Executions and executioners --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  England</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:136980:1"/>
            <head>THE CONFESSION AND EXECUTION OF Mr. Barney, who was Hang'd at NORVVICH, for the Murder of Eſq; Beddingfield Which was commited on <hi>Sunday</hi> the 20th. of <hi>July</hi> 1684.</head>
            <head type="sub">With a true Account of his Behaviour during the time of his Impriſonment, unto the day of his Death, which was on the 8th. of <hi>Aguſt,</hi> 1684.</head>
            <head type="sub">As alſo a true Account of the Fire which happen'd in <hi>Goodmans Fields.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe occaſion of the Quarrel with the attending Circumſtances be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween this unhappy Gentleman, and Mr. <hi>Bedingfield</hi> the World has already been acquainted withal: for which reaſon I ſhall forbear to repeat them, and only wiſh this unfortunate perſon may be the laſt example of publick Juſtice in this Nature. As to his Family he was well deſcended from a worthy Gentleman, a Barronet in the ſame County, whoſe Name and Reputation are yet preſerv'd, beyond the utmoſt Imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Malice, whatever argument from this diſaſter it may ſeem at preſent to be blaſted with.</p>
            <p>At the <hi>Barr,</hi> Mr. <hi>Barny</hi> made all the defence the Nature of his Crime, and the pregnancy of the proofs againſt him would admit of, but being by the Jury brought in guilty, he was condemn'd, and by his Majeſties Gracious Mercy reprieved till this day; when, according to the Sentence of the Court, he ſuffered Death at the common place of Execution, and not at the <hi>Market-Croſs,</hi> as was upon miſtake ſuggeſted in the former Accounts.</p>
            <p>During the time of his Impriſonment, eſpecially after Sentence, and the Account he received by his Friends, there was no hopes of pardon, he beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved himſelf with a Chriſtian patience under ſo great an affliction, and was viſited by ſeveral worthy Divines, who endeavour'd to ſoften his more obdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate heart, by giving him a true repreſentation of that horrid Crime of Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in its due Colours, how heinous an offence it was againſt Heaven, and the preſent Eſtabliſhed Laws by which we all live. The Breach of which demands no other Satisfaction, nor can be obliged with any other propitiato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry than the Blood of him who ſpilt his Neighbours, either from the Violence of Paſſion, or upon more premeditated Malice and Revenge.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:136980:2"/>
            <p>He did, in ſome meaſure, offer to vindicate himſelf from any Cowardize in the Action, and that however the Gentleman Mr. <hi>Beddingfield</hi> happened to be wounded in the back: they were not given by any baſe and indirect means, but that po<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ibly they happened to him in the ſtrugle between them, and that as a Gentleman, he always ſcorn'd a Revenge upon any Perſon but by thoſe means and methods which among Gentlemen, were always thought honourable and generous.</p>
            <p>As to his behaviour as a Chriſtian, no perſon could more expreſly ſpeak his Penitence and Remorſe for ſo great a Crime; and in that interval between the Sentence and the Execution; he paſſed his time in Prayers and Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, confeſſing as a good Chriſtian ought to do, that he had been a great offender, more particularly againſt the Laws of God, and now ſignally againſt thoſe of Man, for which he ſuffered this ſhameful and ignominious Death. Though the Terrors of Death began now to approach him, with all thoſe horrors which may affright the moſt prepared Chriſtian; yet he did not ſeem diſmay'd, but behaved himſelf with the Courage and Reſolution, which a good man would Encounter ſo dreadful an Enemy withal.</p>
            <p>He ſpent the ſhort remainder of his time in reading Religious Books and ſome choice manuals of Devotion, in which he ſeem'd more particularly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted, and as he was extreamly obliged to the great pains and labour of ſome Divines, who were his Friends, and came frequently to viſit him: ſo did he not only pay his thanks and acknowledgements to them in words, but gave more Evident and ſatisfactory Demonſtrations of his Obligations to them by that hearty and ſincere penitence and contrition, which by Gods Grace and their indefatigatiable pains was wrought in him. He gave ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt caution and advice to thoſe Gentlemen who came to ſee him, to have a care of profaning the <hi>Lords Day</hi> and intemperate drinking, both which ſins he had been too frequently guilty of, and which were, in ſome meaſure, the occaſion of his committing this horrid Sin of Murder, for which he now heartily ſorrowed and deſervedly ſuffered. Great interceſſion was made for his Pardon, which could not be obtained.</p>
            <p>ON <hi>Friday,</hi> between the hours of Eleven and Twelve, he was carried to the common place of Execution, where, after ſome ſhort Prayers, he ſuffered according to Law, his Body was put into a Coffin, and delivered to his Friends to interr.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>I ſhall not think it amiſs, to acquaint the <hi>Reader</hi> with this intervene which happen'd in <hi>Goodmans-Fields.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ON <hi>Sunday</hi> Morning, there broke out a moſt furious Fire at the end of a Row of Houl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, near the <hi>Bear Tavarn</hi> towards <hi>Roſemary-Lane;</hi> which was firſt diſcovered by an Inhabitant near the ſaid Houſe; which happened to be up later than ordinary, cryed our fire, which awakened the Neighbouring Inhabitants; who, when they beheld the ſaid Fire was amazed: it beginning at the Top of the Corner-Houſe, at the Eaſt ſide of the Houſe, and ſo burning downward, to the deſtruction of almoſt the firſt Houſe, and hath greatly demoliſh'd the next Houſe adjoyning to it: which was prevented of going any farther, by the aſſiſtance that came in, and the endeavour they made for the quench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame, but no man knowing how it was firſt kindled, but is adjuged by thoſe which firſt ſaw it, to be by the great Thunder and Lightning which was at that <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ime, and not by unſlack'd <hi>Lime</hi> as is reported, by reaſon the <hi>Lime</hi> lay againſt a Brick Wall, and is extremely more ſtrange becauſe it could not be done by the careleſneſs of any workman there that time of Night, but more rather by the immediate hand of God.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notice">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT</head>
            <p>☞ Whereas <hi>George Croom</hi> has at the end of his <hi>Seſſions Paper,</hi> promiſed a moſt true &amp; exact Account of the <hi>Confeſſion</hi> and <hi>Speeches</hi> of the dying Malefactors, and has injuriouſly detracted from the Reputation of others who have better deſerved from Truth than himſelf. Theſe are to acquaint the world, that he has no<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> kept his word with them, but is ſo forward to prefer his own Papers to the Publick, for his private ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, that he often obtrudes falſities upon them; rather than wait with the ſame patience others do, to inquire out the truth of each particular Relation before they make it publick to the world, this is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent in the laſt <hi>Bold and Barbarou's Murder</hi> he printed, committed on <hi>William Culliſord</hi> Eſq; who, bleſſed be God is, only not dead, but in a very hopeful way of Recovery This was deſired to be advertiſed that the world may not be led into Error and Miſtake by his falſe Reports.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>E. M.</hi> in <hi>Black-Horſe Alley</hi> near <hi>Fleet-Bridge.</hi> 1684</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
